<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon on the restoring of the coyn with reference to the state of the nation, and of the church therein / by a minister of the Church of England.</title>
            <author>Minister of the Church of England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59266</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2629</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21327</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12179822</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12179822</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55603</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59266)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55603)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 876:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon on the restoring of the coyn with reference to the state of the nation, and of the church therein / by a minister of the Church of England.</title>
                  <author>Minister of the Church of England.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Jeremiah VI, 30 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Coinage --  Great Britain --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55603:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55603:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON ON The Reſtoring of the COYN, With reference to the State of the Nation, and of the Church therein.</p>
            <p>By a Miniſter of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. 1.25.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>I will turn my hand upon Thee, and purely purge away thy Droſs, and take away all thy Tin.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns,</hi> the lower End of <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers Chapel,</hi> 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:55603:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55603:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipful Sir <hi>Henry Aſhurſt,</hi> Baronet.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is no ſmall inconvenience of the late defici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of the Coin, that it hath occaſion'd ſo much unprofitable Diſcourſe; that in all Companies, almoſt nothing is talked of but Money: There is a Divine Chymiſtry, and Holy Art of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting out of any Common Subject, ſome Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly and Spiritual Matter: It were well if we could take occaſion from the multitude of words about the late debaſed, and now regulated Coin, to affect our own and others Hearts with the depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of our natures, and the neceſſity of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery by Grace; with the Corruption of the Land, and what hope of Reformation; whatever private Perſons may do towards it, at leaſt by earneſt Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and by beginning at home: Church-Reformation is much promoted by Family-Religion, and that muſt begin with perſonal Dedication. It is a true ſaying, <hi>Corruptio optimi eſt peſſima,</hi> next to the Corruption of the Miniſtry, that of the Gentry is moſt to be bewail'd: How ſad is it when they who ſhould help forward the Reformation, do themſelves moſt
<pb facs="tcp:55603:3"/>
need it! But as when the Coin was moſt corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, there was always ſome good, ſo hath the Lord yet a Remnant in this Land, and <hi>the Lord add unto them (how many ſoever they be) an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred fold:</hi> When I have heard of your Zeal for God and his Intereſt in publick and private Stations, I could not but ſay, I have known few a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the great Ones <hi>like minded:</hi> It is upon this account that I have made bold to ſet your Name before this Sermon, that whereas I have not the vanity to think that it ſhould come into the hands of many (if any) of thoſe Noble Patriots to whom I have addreſt my ſelf in the Body of it; the ſubſtance of that part of it may be communicated to them of your acquaintance in your Familiar converſe with them, but in your own more efficacious words, and with greater enlargements than the neceſſity of my keeping within the narrow bounds of a Metaphor would admit of in this Diſcourſe: And yet I have ſaid ſo much to thoſe whom I ſo much reverence, that a modeſt ſhame obligeth me to withdraw my Name, leſt it ſhould be known to come from ſo mean a Perſon; and I ſhall ſeek other ways to make it known, how much I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt Humble, And moſt obliged Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:55603:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JEREMIAH 6.30.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Reprobate Silver ſhall Men call them, becauſe the Lord hath Rejected them.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WHether this Cenſure of the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> be a continuance of Gods words to the Prophet, begun, <hi>ver.</hi> 27. or whether they be the Prophets Words in anſwer to the charge there given him, <hi>I have ſet thee for a Tower—that thou mayeſt know and try their way;</hi> Evident it is, that thereby is repreſented to us the great Corruption of the Church and State of <hi>Iſrael</hi> at that time, under the ſimilitude of Debaſed and Corrupted Coin. <hi>Ver.</hi> 28. <hi>They are grievous Revolters— they are Braſs and Iron, they are all Corrupters.</hi> Which is further am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plified, 1. By the Pains that had been taken, and Means uſed to remedy this Corruption. <hi>Ver.</hi> 29. <hi>The Bellows are burnt, the Lead is conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of the Fire, the Founder melts in vain: for the wicked are not plucked away.</hi> 2. By the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting and Caſting them off, thereupon <hi>Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate Silver,</hi> Refuſe Coin <hi>ſhall Men call them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lord hath rejected them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:55603:4"/>Doct. <hi>The State of a Church, with reſpect to the degeneracy of the People, is like that of a Land, with reſpect to the debaſing of the Coin; they are like Reprobate, Refuſe, and Rejected Money.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame ſimilitude is uſed by the other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.22. <hi>Thy Silver is become Droſs.</hi> Ezek. 22.18. <hi>The houſe of Iſrael is to me become Droſs, all they are Braſs, and Tin, and Iron, and Lead in the midſt of the Furnace.</hi> Which is not ſpoken as to thoſe Metals in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but as uſed to Corrupt the Silver, and Debaſe the Coin, which Metaphor is largely perſued in the following verſes, to note how they were like Money, that was firſt Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, then Reprobated and Refus'd, which the Government would Reject, and forbid to be Own'd, or to paſs Currant any more; <hi>Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate Silver ſhall Men call them,</hi> &amp;c. What the Caſe of this Land hath been, with reſpect to the debaſing of the Coin, almoſt every one is ſenſible of, and hath felt more or leſs; Had it not been timely reſtor'd, it might have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ruin to the Nation: Now this ſimilitude doth ſo ſuit the Condition of this poor Church
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:55603:4"/>
and Nation, with reſpect to our great dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neracy, that unleſs ſomething be done for a more effectual remedy, our Caſe muſt needs be ſad indeed. The conſidering of the Parallels in the Doctrinal Part, may help to prepare us for the Application.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Heretofore there was good Coin, of the right Stamp, of the full Weight; <hi>Currant Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney of the Merchant.</hi> The conveniency and uſefulneſs of which for Trade and Commerce no one doubts of: Now this doth aptly ſet forth the happy condition of a Nation where Religion flouriſheth; and Holineſs and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs are, as it were, the currant Coin of it. That place in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 1.22. that ſpeaks of the debaſing the Silver, hath reference to what goes before, <hi>ver.</hi> 21. <hi>It was a faithful City, it was full of Judgment, Righteouſneſs lodged in it:</hi> It was <hi>pure Coin,</hi> though now <hi>Adulterated.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed if we were to ſeek for a time when there was no corrupt Money in the Land, we muſt run it up to Ages long ſince paſt; So if we ſeek for perfect Purity, we muſt look as far, as to the ſtate before the Fall, when God <hi>made Man upright,</hi> and inſtamped upon him <hi>his own image,</hi> and there was no diſagreement from the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:55603:5"/>
Standard and Rule of his Holy Law: Yet there have been days ſince that, when there hath been a greater comparative Purity, as in the primitive times of Chriſtianity, and next to them in the year after the Reformation; ſo that it might be ſaid of the Churches that they were like pure Silver Coin in the ſame reſpect, as it was ſaid of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in that forecited place, in the days of <hi>Aſa</hi> and <hi>Jehoſaphat:</hi> And though it cannot be deny'd that there may be a great fault in ſaying, <hi>The former times were better than theſe,</hi> Eccleſ. 7.10. Yet that is to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid a murmuring at the Judgments in our days, and not to prevent our Humiliation for the ſins of them; though there hath been all along ſome bad Money, yet we can all remember the time when it was much better than of late: here were Faults and Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the days of our Fathers, but it is yet within the memory of ſome alive, when there was not ſuch a flood of Debauchery as hath broken in ſince; and many that are no ways factiouſly inclined, have given a true Report, of that Zeal for God that was amongſt the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of Religion heretofore, that ſeriouſneſs in their Families, circumſpection in their lives;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:55603:5"/>
of that encouragement that the power of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs met with, from Perſons of Great Name and Note, in the Counties and Places where they dwelt</p>
            <p n="2">2. There hath been of late a great debaſing of the Coin. Part of it Embezelled, and the weight Diminiſhed; part of it Adulterated, the Stamp Chang'd; ſome plain Braſs to every eye, the reſt more cunningly Counterfeited, but preſently diſcovered by a more diſcerning ſight. The dangerous condition in which the Land was a while ago on this account, doth repreſent to us our danger ſtill with reſpect to higher Corruptions; where it is to be hoped that there may be the True Stamp ſtill; Yet is our Spiritual ſtate like that of the Coin, <hi>Impair'd;</hi> the Ancient Seriouſneſs, Piety and Charity, much clipt off; the Letters miſſing by which it was wont to be known; <hi>by this ſhall all men know that you are my Diſciples, if you love one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother;</hi> Our diviſions have been to us what the Sheers and ſuch like Inſtruments, have been to the Money. With others it hath been yet far worſe; there is nothing of the Royal Coin left; they have another Stamp upon <hi>Braſs</hi> and <hi>Iron</hi> waſh'd over, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.18. What a mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:55603:6"/>
of falſe Doctrines and Blaſphemies (witneſs the late ſpreading of Socinianiſm and Deiſm) of Debauchery, and wicked Practices, Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs, Uncleanneſs and Prophanation of the Lord's Name and Day, hath there been with the poor remainder of a Chriſtian Profeſſion! The Braſs is apparent, <hi>By their Works you ſhall know them:</hi> Though others have cunningly diſguiſed their Wickedneſs, who yet lye open to the All-diſcerning Eye of him, <hi>who trys the Hearts and the Reins.</hi> It is true, the Corruption of the Coin was not all at once, but in a few Months ſpace, it grew worſe at laſt than in many years before. The ſinful Corruption of this Nation hath been a gradual thing, and whither will it proceed if it be not yet at the height, and if ſome ſtop be not put to the day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly increaſe? Already is the Land reduc'd to as miſerable a Caſe, as ever the Coin was. For, (1.) Sin has obſcur'd the glory of it: There was always ſome good pieces where the Coin were at worſt, and uſually ſome Silver in the moſt debaſed Piece, but the luſtre of the Coin was loſt It is (2.) rendred Deceitful and Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritical, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> was call'd, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.6. The Counterfeit Coin was perpetually cheating, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:55603:6"/>
deceiving thoſe that had to do with it. And thereby (3.) It is become worthleſs and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible, <hi>nigh unto curſing,</hi> ready to be <hi>rejected,</hi> like Coin that could not be uſed, it was ſo Adulterated, or as the Prophet uſeth another ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude, <hi>Jer.</hi> 24.8. <hi>Like figs that could not be eaten, they were ſo evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Many attemps were made to prevent the miſchief, but all prov'd ineffectual, ſo long as the corrupted Coin was ſuffered to paſs cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. Indeed the more ignorant ſort ſaw not the cauſe of the Miſchief, nor the need of a remedy: They thought and ſaid, <hi>That if their Money might but paſs according to its denominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, tho' it was made of Leather, it was all one to them.</hi> Others that underſtood better did dread the conſequences, and did ſomething to prevent them; private Perſons in their places, and the Governours in theirs; many of the counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit Pieces were ſtopt, and broken, that they might cheat no more; many of the Debaſers and Coiners were taken and <hi>ſuffered the due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of their deeds;</hi> but all this was inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to put a ſtop to the Corruption, on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, it grew worſe and worſe. This is ſet down in the verſe before the Text, <hi>v.</hi> 29. <hi>The Bellows ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burnt,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:55603:7"/>
the Lead is conſumed of the fire, the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der melteth in vain: for the wicked are not plucked away.</hi> Which may in the general Note, that the Land in reſpect of Moral Corruption, was not only like debaſed Coin, but worſe; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was more eaſie to redreſs the State of the Coin than of the Land: But indeed this verſe hath ſome difficulty as to the Application of the Metaphor, for the <hi>fire</hi> is wont to be the laſt remedy, and to prove effectual to the deſigned end, and ſo we find it uſed in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel places, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.25, 26. <hi>Ezek</hi> 22.22. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive therefore that the ſimililtude muſt ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie ſomething elſe <hi>here,</hi> and ſomething leſs than it doth in the other places, <hi>viz.</hi> The Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory and Precious Methods that were uſed (before the <hi>Rejection</hi> ſpoken of in the Text) which all miſcarry'd: Here were <hi>Bellows</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, and <hi>Lead</hi> (uſed then inſtead of Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilver) to have facilitated the melting; here was the <hi>Founder</hi> ready, but all <hi>in vain,</hi> Why? <hi>becauſe the wicked was not plucked away.</hi> The debaſed Coin was ſtill Currant; the Founder melts his Lead, and conſumes it for nothing. Hath it not been thus in our Land? It is a ſtrange ſtupidity of ſome, that they are
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:55603:7"/>
againſt all attempts of a Reformation; they would have all things go as they do; Hereſies, and Debaucheries let alone: But yet attempts have been made, ſome private ſtop put to the Corruption in ſome places; Publick Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt Debaucheries, Orders againſt He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, Commiſſions and Conſultations about Church Reformation. Nay, here hath been ſomething of the <hi>Fire</hi> kindled, the <hi>Bellows</hi> and <hi>Lead</hi> prepared. Noting either the preaching of the Word, or the preparatory Judgments of Plague, Fire, Wars, and ſuch like <hi>Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> all which are ineffectual <hi>becauſe the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed are not plucked away.</hi> It ſtill grew worſe while the debaſed Coin paſt currant.</p>
            <p n="4">4. At laſt the Government reſolv'd to make a thorough work; they wholly <hi>rejected</hi> the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſed Coin, that it ſhould no more paſs by the Name it did (<hi>Reprobate,</hi> or Refuſe, <hi>Silver ſhall Men call it.</hi>) They order'd all the corrupted Money to be brought to the fire, that nothing ſhould go but according to Weight and Standard, and that the whole at laſt ſhould be made New, more excellent for beauty, ſafety and uſefulneſs than ever before. <hi>The Lord hath rejected it,</hi> ſaith the Text; But, alas! <hi>who ſhall
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:55603:8"/>
live when God will do this?</hi> When (1) God ſhall pour contempt upon the prophane in the eyes of the World, and ſhall <hi>ſeparate the precious from the vile;</hi> So that they ſhall not paſs currant as Men in faſhion that blaſpheme the Name of God with their horrid Oaths, and ridicule Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion as a Cheat and Prieſtcraft; when they ſhall not call the <hi>proud happy,</hi> but, <hi>Reprobate Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall Men call them.</hi> When (2.) all things ſhall go by weight and meaſure, as reduc'd to the ſtandard of the Word; when things ſhall not go by meer name, as we have called that a Shilling which was not half weight, nor a quarter worth but as <hi>weigh'd in the Ballance of the Sanctuary.</hi> When (3.) upon bringing the rejected and refuſe Silver to the flame, <hi>all things ſhall become new,</hi> and the Church re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor'd to its Beauty and Excellency as the Coin is. This is admirably repreſented, in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.19,— 22. and in other places. Now whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever way the Lord will work this, whether by Magiſtrates whom he will ſpirit and ſtir up for it; or by Afflictions, ſometimes called a <hi>Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace;</hi> or by greater Effuſions of his Spirit in the preaching of the Word; or whether by all theſe together, ſure we are, <hi>that he will be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:55603:8"/>
like a refiners fire,</hi> Mal. 3.2. And there will be theſe two things in it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Great Wrath upon ſuch as ſhall be found debaſed and corrupted, and ſo refuſed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 119.119. <hi>Thou putteſt away all the wicked of the Earth like droſs;</hi> They deſpiſed God, his Ways and his People, they counted them as the Off-ſcouring of the World, and they themſelves ſhall be lightly eſteem'd, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.20, 21. <hi>As they gather Silver, and Braſs, and Iron, and Lead, and Tin, into the midſt of the Furnace to blow the fire upon it, ſo will I gather you in mine anger and my fury—and I will blow upon you in the fire of my wrath,</hi> &amp;c. The Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God are very ſearching and deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting upon the wicked many times in this World, as we have inſtances in Church-Hiſtory all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, even ſo as to be an Emblem of the great Judgment to come, and to expreſs, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. 3— <hi>I will come upon thee, and thou ſhalt not know what hour I will come upon thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Great Mercy to the Church afterwards, for upon the rejecting the wicked, the Church is reſtored, <hi>Prov.</hi> 25.4. <hi>Take away the Droſs
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:55603:9"/>
from the Silver, and there ſhall come forth a Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel for the Finer;</hi> which is apply'd in the next Words to the <hi>taking away the wicked</hi>— verſe 5. Divers of the Prophets ſpake of this <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.3. <hi>He ſhall ſit as a Refiner, and Purifier of Silver: and he ſhall purifie the Sons of</hi> Levi, <hi>and purge them as Gold and Silver, that they may offer to the Lord an offering in Righteouſneſs.</hi> He may poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly begin with them in Judgment for their Corruptions, and in Mercy for their Recovery, that they may be inſtruments in reſtoring others. Of whom another Prophet ſpeaks in the ſame manner, <hi>Zech.</hi> 13.9. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs, that in all the Land ſaith the Lord, two parts therein ſhall be cut off and die, but the third ſhall be left therein; and I will bring the third part through the fire, and will refine them as Silver is refin'd, and will try them as Gold is tried: they ſhall call upon my Name, and I will hear them,</hi> &amp;c. Here is a remnant reſerv'd and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor'd, made bright and Illuſtrious, like New and Beautiful Coin. The like we may ſee in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.25. and 4.3, 4. Of which, further Uſe may be made in the Application, to which we ſhall now proceed.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:55603:9"/>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. This may be uſed for a ſerious Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, that you be not found amongſt the Corrupters, and Corrupted Ones, whom the Lord will reject. The old debaſed Coin paſt a great while; it went currant, partly through faultineſs, and partly through ignorance; <hi>The wicked have not been plucked away;</hi> ſome have continued in the Church through neglect of Diſcipline, and others by reaſon of their Waſhes and cunning Artifices have not been diſcovered to be what they are: What will you do when you can paſs currant to longer? <hi>there is a day that will manifeſt every mans work, for the fire will declare it.</hi> If thou continueſt a prophane Enemy of God and Godlineſs, a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant Hater of ſeriouſneſs and ſtrictneſs in Religion; if under the waſh of an outward Profeſſion, thou wilt ſtill cheriſh Malice, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, Worldlineſs, or ſuch like Luſts in thy Heart, thou wilt be <hi>rejected,</hi> refuſe Coin, <hi>repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated,</hi> and caſt off by the Lord <hi>Hearken</hi> therefore in time to the Word of the Lord, <hi>that God may hearken unto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:55603:10"/>1. See that you have the image of God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtamp'd and renewed upon your Souls: When the Coin was debaſed, they melted down the Money that had the right ſtamp they corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it with the baſer Metals of Braſs and Iron, and placed a counterfeit Stamp upon it; this was our ruine at firſt: By the Fall the Image of God was loſt, and defac'd, and a contrary <hi>image</hi> ſtamp'd on the Soul: There muſt be a reſtoring the King's <hi>Image</hi> again, the debaſed Coin muſt be broken with the Hammer, melted with the fire, and made ſuſceptible of a new ſtamp; How admirably doth this ſet forth the work of Grace upon the Heart! <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.29. <hi>Is not my word like a Fire, ſaith the Lord? and like a Hammer that breaketh the Rock in pieces?</hi> Thou muſt be broken by the Hammer of the Law, and melted down by the Goſpel, and the Lord's <hi>Image</hi> muſt be renewed upon thy Soul, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.10. <hi>And have put on the new Man which is renewed in Knowledge, after the Image of him that Created him.</hi> And in the other E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.24. it is ſaid to be after God, that is, <hi>after his Image,</hi> which we are told there, doth conſiſt <hi>in Righteouſneſs and true Holineſs.</hi> So that the great Queſtion, which you muſt put
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:55603:10"/>
to your Souls, is, <hi>Whoſe is this Image and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription?</hi> Is it after <hi>Chriſt,</hi> after his likeneſs? have you receiv'd <hi>Grace for Grace?</hi> Is there Grace in you, anſwering to the great Patterns and <hi>Exemplar</hi> in him, as in the Coin <hi>face an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to face,</hi> and one part and feature to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? It will come to that at laſt, that no Coin will go currant, but what is new. <hi>All old things muſt paſs away, and all things become new,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.17. The Apoſtles words reſpect another ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude, but may be applyed to this, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7. That you muſt <hi>be a new lump,</hi> or Maſs, on which a new <hi>Image</hi> muſt be ſtamp'd. There muſt be <hi>a new Heart and a new Spirit,</hi> Ezek. 36.26. From whence proceeds <hi>newneſs</hi> of Life and Obedience: And as the old Coin is ſtill wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away, and the new Money increaſing; ſo muſt the <hi>old Man</hi> be decaying, as <hi>cruciſi'd with Chriſt,</hi> Rom 6.6. put to a lingering death, till at laſt there be no more of it; and the <hi>new man</hi> muſt increaſe, till Grace comes to be perfected in Glory.</p>
            <p n="2">2 See that in your whole life and courſe you be according to the <hi>Standard,</hi> and full Weight. It was the charge upon that Remiſs Church of <hi>Sardis,</hi> in which we are nearly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:55603:11"/>
               <hi>that the Lord had not found her works perfect before God,</hi> Rev. 3 2. <hi>not filled up;</hi> but like Coin impaird and embezelled, that would not hold weight. The Goſpel requires good Works, as well as the Law, though not for the ſame ends: and the one is a <hi>Standard</hi> as well as the other, if he weighs us in the Ballance of his Law, and Covenant of Works there is no Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, but that of Chriſts, which will hold weight: But ſincerity is a kind of Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal perfection, and ſo own'd in the Covenant of Grace; and ſad is our caſe, if God ſhould write upon us, <hi>TEKEL, thou art weigh'd in the Ballances, and art found wanting,</hi> Dan. 5.27. There are many frothy vain Perſons of empty light Spirits that have no ſolidity; <hi>Examine your ſelves,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>prove your own ſelves,</hi> 2 Cor. 13.5. Where he uſeth a word, that is alſo made uſe of for the Tryal of Metals of which Money is made.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. This may further be improv'd by way of caution, that you take heed of murmuring and fretting about the difficulties occaſion'd by the Coin at this day, when you have more reaſon to lye low before God in ſorrow,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:55603:11"/>
and humiliation. Murmuring hath been one of the prevailing ſins of <hi>England</hi> of late, as it was of the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> when they came out of <hi>Aegypt;</hi> there are many circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances that are much alike in both Nothing hath more exercis'd the Tongues, and fill'd the Hearts of many this laſt year, than the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties about the Money: <hi>No Man ſmites upon his thigh and crys, what have I done?</hi> Each one murmuring at others, the wiſeſt Councellour and Counſels cannot eſcape them; they <hi>fret themſelves againſt God and the King, and look up.</hi> Sometimes they murmur at the inconveniencies occaſion'd by the Calling in of the Coin, the ſtoppage of their Trade and Commerce, the hinderance of the War, and of the Peace, and Deliverance hop'd for by it; at other times at the difficulties in amending the Coin, the delay of it, and the fruſtrating ſome attempts that have been made to reſtore it.</p>
            <p>Now not to argue againſt this murmuring from the General Heads of the Sin and danger of it; I deſire only that they who murmur in this Caſe, would reflect upon themſelves, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire whether they have not more cauſe to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:55603:12"/>
mourn, than to fret upon this account. Let it be conſidered:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether you are not the Perſons that have cauſed this Calamity, this Debaſing of the Coin; I do not mean, whether your ſins as well as others, have caus'd it meretoriouſly, as ſin brings down all Judgments, but whether you have not been inſtrumental in procuring theſe inconveniencies, which have lain heavy on your ſelves and others. They that ſuffer'd juſtly for their Treaſon, and a kind of Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery of the whole Nation, in Clipping and Coining, were not the only guilty Perſons; it muſt needs be that they have other Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates, Acceſſaries to their Treaſon and Theft, who helpt them to all that broad Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney which they clipt and melted down; which Confederacy is doubtleſs an <hi>Iniquity,</hi> that ought to be puniſhed by the <hi>Judges;</hi> but I hope this guilt lies (comparitively) but among a few. There is yet a more general Sin to be bewailed, which was always accounted a hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous piece of injuſtice, till the temptation grew too ſtrong for many; the putting off falſe and counterfeit Money in their dealings one with
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:55603:12"/>
another. How many made no conſcience of putting off Braſs and Iron for Silver, becauſe, ſay they, we took it for good our ſelves; which is but in other words, to cheat others, becauſe they themſelves were impos'd upon! It was this common practice that encourag'd the pouring in ſuch vaſt quantities of debaſed Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney upon us: I doubt not, now the Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is over, the Conviction will be more eaſie, that it is the ſame ſin to put off counterfeit Money knowingly, as to put off counterfeit Goods: A ſin ſo general, ought to be publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledged, and bewail'd by the Land; and ſhall the guilty perſons murmur at that which they caus'd; at an Evil which they have encouraged and procured!</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether you your ſelves are not like this debaſed Coin, this <hi>reprobate Silver,</hi> this refuſe Money, which is now <hi>rejected?</hi> How little good, and how much bad would there be found, if now you are brought to the Ballance? Let me only put the Queſtion to your Hearts in reference to the pretences of your preſent Murmuring.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:55603:13"/>1. You murmur, that the badneſs and defici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of the Coin hath hindred your Trade, and ſtopt the ſucceſs of the War; upon this ſome fly out into extravagant expreſſions, which I liſt not to repeat. Now I beſeech you conſider whether the greater corruption of your lives hath not more hindred the progreſs of the Goſpel, and the deſired deliverance. Is not the Goſpel of more concern than your Trade, and the intereſt of Chriſt in the Land than your private intereſt? and yet this is that which you have hindred. You are degenerated and debaſed, become, as the Prophet ſaith, <hi>Braſs, Tin, Iron</hi> and <hi>Lead; Braſs</hi> for Impudence in Sin, <hi>Tin</hi> for Hypocriſie, <hi>Iron</hi> for inflexibleneſs, <hi>Lead</hi> for ſtupidity; and hath not this more hindred the work of God in the Land, than the bad Money hath hindred your work? You your ſelves have been the <hi>Achans</hi> that have <hi>troubled our Iſrael:</hi> It was not the want or the badneſs of the Coin that hindred the ſucceſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Enemy, ſo much as the abounding of ſin in the Land. <hi>Oh that my People had hearkned unto me, and Iſrael had walked in my ways, I ſhould ſoon have ſubdued their Enemies, and turned my hand againſt their Adverſaries,</hi> Pſal. 81.13, 14.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:55603:13"/>Or, 2. You murmur that there are delays in amending and reſtoring the Coin, that ſome attempts have fail'd, and many diſappointments are met with that were not expected: But ought you not to conſider, how many more apparent miſcarriages there have been of the attempts to reform you? Here have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lays as to the Coin, but you ſee ſomething is done; a great deal of new Money is come abroad, but what hath yet been done amongſt you? though ſome attempts as to the Money, have miſcarried, yet others do ſucceed; but all the ſeveral methods to reform you have in great part failed. Such exceeding difficulties do they meet with, who have attempted a greater purity in Church and State, that they are ready to give it over, as a hopeleſs under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking. So refractory have Sinners prov'd, and averſe to Reformation, that there is need of all fitting Arguments to perſuade thoſe, whoſe work it is, to overcome the diſcouragements they have met with, and to ſet about it, in good earneſt; which brings us to another Uſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3. By way of Addreſs and humble Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to them who have been the Reſtorers
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:55603:14"/>
of our Coin, that they may become <hi>healers of our breaches, and reſtorers of paths to dwell in.</hi> I doubt not when the heat of Mens paſſions is a little over, the whole Nation will thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully acknowledge your Wiſdom and Care in the late Regulation of the Money; and the more ſerious part of it will eſpecially take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of your delivering us from ſo great a Snare, as was the cuſtomary putting off bad Money to one another, almoſt at laſt without Reluctancy. Now it hath been prov'd that our Land is become by ſin, like corrupted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſed Coin, and that the Reformation of it is Gods Work, who uſeth what inſtruments he pleaſeth; And Oh that it might pleaſe him to put it into your hearts to do as much for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of his Church, as you have done for the intereſt of the Nation! that you may reſolve to ſit <hi>de die in Diem,</hi> as one <hi>grand Committee for Religion,</hi> till all things are brought to the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, and reduc'd to the great Standard of the Word. You have been ſenſible how much the honour of the King is concern'd, that the Coin ſhould be ſuch as he ſhould own; and is not the Lord as jealous of his Miniſtry and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, on which he hath ſet his Stamp? I will
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:55603:14"/>
only ſet before you, your own example, Do as you have done for us, <hi>and the Lord ſhall be with you.</hi> You have delivered us from the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted Coin, you have refuſed and <hi>rejected</hi> it; deliver us alſo effectually from Debaucheries and Prophaneneſs; put a greater reſtraint upon the boldneſs of Hereticks, <hi>that deny the Lord that bought them;</hi> what you find amiſs in the Church, redreſs it; and begin, as God himſelf doth, with <hi>the Sons of Levi.</hi> His Majeſties Commiſſion to the late Convocation, 1689. will inform you of the particular grievances, and you do not want eminent Lights ſet up in the higheſt places of the Church, to aſſiſt you in the redreſſing of them. You have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged the good Money to come abroad freely, which heretofore was hoarded up; and can it be for the glory of God, that ſo many Perſons ſhould be hoarded up, and confin'd to private &amp; ſeparate Aſſemblies, whoſe Labours are much wanted in the Church, had the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion gone along with the <hi>Toleration</hi> ſeven years ago, it had doubtleſs been more for the intereſt of Religion in general, as well as for the Church of <hi>England</hi> in particular. You have taken care, that the old Money, not yet ſpoil'd,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:55603:15"/>
ſhould be Recalled and Recoined: It hath been formerly unqueſtionably currant, the Nation hath flouriſhed in the uſe thereof, yet when you ſaw that the Hammered Coin was liable to be abuſed ſtill, and like to breed quarrels amongſt the People, in Wiſdom you thought fit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move it, and to exchange it for that which is more bright, and ſafe, and uſefull: Let it pleaſe you to conſider, whether there be not ſome <hi>Rites and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſages,</hi> thô not debaſed by ſuperſtition, yet unneceſſary and ſubject to abuſes, <hi>which have bred quarrels in the Church for above a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years together,</hi> and whether they may not be chang'd for ſuch as are more unqueſtionably uſeful: eſpecially when this difference is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, that the old Money which you call in, hath had on it the Royal Stamp, whereas theſe Uſages pretend only to a bare allowance to paſs for a time, and are more like to the ſmall Money, which I remember many years ago was ſtampt by private Shop keepers, which by the leave of the Government, went currant for ſome years, within the narrow Bounds aſſigned them: But it hath ſince been found much better, that even Farthings ſhould have the King's Stamp, and nothing ſuffered but what may paſs currant through the Land.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:55603:15"/>I doubt not but in the ſetting about ſo great a work as is the Reforming a corrupted Land, you will meet with many difficulties, and you will not want thoſe who will on purpoſe lay rubs in your way; but give me leave to ſay, they can propoſe no Objections, but what you have anſwer'd your ſelves, nor are there any Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions but what you have already broke through in the like caſe.</p>
            <p>Should it be objected that we have a good eſtabliſhment already, that there are many good Law's againſt corruptions in the Land, many good Conſtitutions in the Church, and actual endeavours already made for a Reformation of what is amiſs; was it not alſo ſo as to the Coin? was there not a good eſtabliſhment of it former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, good Laws about the taking and refuſing it, and care taken for the preventing and redreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the abuſes of it? yet you ſaw cauſe to do ſomething more, and more effectually than ever had been done before in our days.</p>
            <p>It will be objected, That alterations are dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous; there will be thoſe that will cry out, as if the Church were in danger, if you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move but a Ceremony, but you have got over this ſtumbling Block too; for there have not
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:55603:16"/>
wanted thoſe that would have amuſed you and the Nation, with fears and jealouſies, as if you were ruining the Land, when you were reſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Coin. You eaſily perceiv'd that theſe out-crys came from a ſelfiſh private intereſt, and unconcernedneſs for the publick good.</p>
            <p>It may poſſibly be further ſaid, that ſhould you do all that is deſired, there would be ſtill faults and corruptions, ſtill quarrels and factions, that ſome Men will never be ſatisfied, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is done in, and for the Church; and is not the ſame thing ſaid as to the Coin, that there will be Counterfeits of the New Money too; quarrels amongſt the people about it, and ſome diſſatisfied as well as others pleaſed? Let not Objections, already baffled, and anſwered, by your ſelves have any force to hinder you in ſo great a work. And yet there is need of one Uſe of the Doctrine more.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 4. To ſtir us up to a ſolemn Supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto, and entire dependance upon the Lord to perform his own Work, in his own way. The Church needs and calls for the prayers of all the Members of it; and the promiſes of God are <hi>the ground of our Faith, and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:55603:16"/>
of our prayers,</hi> Iſa. 1.25, 26. <hi>I will turn my hand upon thee, and purely purge away thy droſs, and take away all they Tin; And I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore thy Judges as at the firſt, and thy Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours as at the beginning; afterwards thou ſhalt be called the City of Righteouſneſs, the faithful City.</hi> Indeed if we conſider Gods rejecting the wicked as <hi>Reprobate Silver,</hi> abſtractedly and by it ſelf, it ſeems rather matter of trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, than of deſire: When the Pſalmiſt had ſaid, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 119.119. <hi>Thou putteſt away all the Wicked of the Earth as droſs-</hi>he adds <hi>v.</hi> 120. <hi>My fleſh trembles for fear of thee.</hi> But when we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, in reference to his deſign, the purifying and beautifying his Church, the preſerving and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending it from all that would miſchief it How could all they <hi>who make mention of the Lord not keep ſilence,</hi> but pray more earneſtly, <hi>and give him no reſt till he hath made</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>a praiſe in the Earth;</hi> till the name and image of our King be again viſible on all his Coin; as he hath ſaid, <hi>I will write on it the name of my God, and the name of the City of my God,</hi> Rev. 3.13. till that, which is the inſcription on the Coin, ſhall be written round the Church,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:55603:17"/>
               <hi>Decus &amp; Tutamen,</hi> Glory and Defence: Which is directly according to his promiſe, for having ſpoken of <hi>Purging</hi> of his Church, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 4.4. <hi>With the Spirit of Judgment, and the Spirit of Burning;</hi> according to the alluſion of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finers Fire:</hi> He adds, <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>That upon all the glory there ſhall be a defence.</hi> Which two things are again propheſied of, <hi>Zech.</hi> 2.5. <hi>I will be unto her a Wall of fire, and the glory in the midſt of her.</hi> What <hi>Glory, Luſtre</hi> and <hi>Beauty</hi> will the Church then have, when the <hi>Lord ſhall turn to the people a pure Language, and they ſhall call on him, and ſerve him with one conſent?</hi> Zeph. 3.9. And for <hi>Defence; He ſhall fill</hi> Zion <hi>with Judgment, and Righteouſneſs, and Knowledge ſhall be the ſtability of our times,</hi> Iſa. 33.6. <hi>Then ſhalt thou no more be termed</hi> Deſolate, <hi>nor thy Land</hi> Forſaken, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.4. <hi>As now men call it repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate Silver, rejected and refuſe, but thou ſhalt be called,</hi> Hephzibah, <hi>and thy Land,</hi> Beulah: <hi>for the Lord delighteth in thee, and thy Land ſhall be married— As the Bridegroom rejoiceth over the Bried, ſo ſhall they God rejoice over thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
